I was not going to make another video on
covered calls, but I was at a retail
investor conference recently. That's me
and the plain bagel up on stage and I
spent the day talking to retail
investors. It struck me how hard the
conference attendees were being sold on
covered call funds and how frequently I
was being asked about them. When I made
my last video on this topic, I honestly
did not realize how widespread this
financial had become. These
products are likely to be detrimental to
long-term investors, including those who
need income. And I think it's important
for the truth about what they should be
expected to do to be articulated in an
understandable way. I'm Ben Felix, chief
investment officer at PWL Capital, and
I'm going to tell you again why the
passive income from covered calls is a
financial
I'm going to start with some quick
background uncovered calls, go through
some live fund examples with reasonably
long-term data, including dividend
reinvestment, and then go through
similar examples modeling spending from
the portfolios. As you will see, even in
that case, covered calls perform worse
than their underlying equities. If you
stick around to the end of the video, I
also have some comments on whether I, as
a chief investment officer and portfolio
manager, am professionally threatened by
covered calls and also why people need
to be aware of incentives when they are
consuming information. Covered calls are
a perfect storm of financial innovation,
which tends to favor the financial
product provider more than the end
consumer, and investor biases, which
lead people to seek income producing
investments without realizing the cost
to total returns. Selling a call option
means selling someone the right to buy a
stock from you at a predetermined price
called the strike price in exchange for
a premium. Say the stock is trading at
$100. You sell a call option with a
strike price of $15 and you collect a $2
premium. The effect of this trade will
depend on the future price of the stock.
If the stock stays below $105, the
option expires worthless. you keep the
$2 premium, which means in this whole
light green shaded range in the chart,
you're always doing a little bit better
than if you had just held the stock. As
long as the stock stays above $98,
you're not losing any money on the
trade. If the stock rises above $15, the
option gets exercised. Your upside is
capped. You do make $5 from the stock
price increase plus the $2 premium from
selling the option. That's a maximum
profit of $7 on the trade. If the price
goes higher than that, you don't
participate in the upside. The line on
the payoff diagram flattens right there.
Compared to simply holding the stock,
you're ahead as long as the price stays
below $17. That's the strike price plus
the premium. But once it climbs past
$17, you would have been better off
without the covered call. And on the
downside, say the stock crashes to $50,
you still pocket the $2 premium, but
you're taking nearly the full hit on the
price decline of the shares. The premium
softens the blow a little tiny bit on
the downside, but your downside risk is
mostly unchanged from simply owning the
stock. A fund using the strategy
typically distributes the option
premiums from selling calls to
investors, resulting in their high
distribution yields. Those distribution
yields are misleading due to their
effect on total returns. Remember,
selling the call is only the first step
in the trade. The fund has sold the
right to buy the underlying stock at the
strike price. If the price of the
underlying rises above the strike price,
the option holder, whoever the fund sold
the option to, will exercise their call
option and the fund will have to sell
their stock at a price below its market
value, putting a cap on upside returns.
The result is that selling the call has
reduced exposure to the underlying
equity primarily on the upside while
downside returns remained largely
exposed, reducing expected returns and
capping the ability of the fund to
recover after the inevitable downturns
that stocks experience. For long-term
investors, my view is that covered call
funds are not good investments. They do
not generate passive income and they
create unnecessary layers of risk and
cost. This is also true for investors
who need income as I will show you with
five examples in just a minute. These
funds create the illusion of income
while systematically lowering expected
returns and increasing risk by changing
the shape of the distribution of
returns. One of the most common
questions that I got on my last video
was whether my performance comparisons
assumed the reinvestment of
distributions. The yields on these
covered call funds are incredibly high.
So distributions being reinvested or not
does matter a lot. I can confirm that my
performance comparisons did assume
reinvestment of distributions and they
will in this video too. Let's look at
some quick examples. The Global X S&P
500 covered call ETF has trailed the
EyesShares Core S&P 500 ETF by an
annualized 3.15 percentage points since
January 2014. The Global X S&P TSX 60
covered call ETF has trailed the
Eyesshares S&P TSX60 ETF by 3.81
percentage points since March 2011. and
the BIMO covered call Canadian banks ETF
has trailed the BEIMO equal weight banks
ETF by an annualized 2.86 percentage
points since February 2011. An important
question is whether total returns which
we just looked at are the right metric
for an income oriented investor. The
premise here is that showing wealth
accumulation and annualized returns, as
I just did, might itself be misleading
if covered calls actually perform better
in a scenario where funds from the
portfolio are needed each month to buy
your groceries and pay your property
taxes or rent or whatever. I'm going to
address this with a simple portfolio
withdrawal analysis. I have 10 years of
data for five pairs of funds. Each pair
has a covered call fund and a fund of
the underlying equity or a very close
proxy for the underlying equity. In my
model, the investor in the covered call
fund is spending approximately the
fund's distributions while the investor
in the underlying equities will spend
the same dollar amount as the covered
call investor each month through a
combination of portfolio dividends and
selling shares. I'll say it again since
this is really important to the example.
They are both spending the exact same
dollar amount each month. But the
investor in the regular equity fund in
the underlying equities is creating
their own income through a combination
of dividends and sales from the
portfolio. Believe it or not, whether
your returns come from income or
capital, it is the combination of the
two, the total return that actually
matters for funding your consumption.
And it is possible, contrary to popular
belief, to spend from the capital
portion of a portfolio sustainably. If
you do not believe this to be true, you
are suffering from the mental accounting
bias and it may be costing you a lot as
we are about to see. This withdrawal
analysis will give us ending portfolio
values to compare where a higher
portfolio value, remember holding
withdrawal amounts constant in dollar
terms suggests a better outcome. After
running through the withdrawal
scenarios, I found that not one of the
covered call funds had higher ending
wealth after 10 years than a comparable
fund of the underlying equities. The
investor in the underlying spent the
same dollar amount as the covered call
investor each month and had on average
26% more capital left after 10 years.
Mind-blowing passive investment income
in shambles. I was not surprised by this
and you should not be either. Covered
calls are capping upside returns without
offering downside protection and their
yield is far from sufficient to offset
the lost upside. The implied cost of
these products is substantial. I solved
for the non- taxdeductible fee that you
would have to pay to invest in the
underlying equity funds such that the
ending wealth outcomes are equal to
their covered call counterparts. The
break even fee was between 1.5 and 2.7%
depending on the fund. That's not to
suggest that you should be paying a fee
that high to invest. It just illustrates
how much the covered call strategy is
costing you relative to simply investing
in the underlying equities and creating
your own income stream by receiving
dividends and selling some shares. The
other thing I looked at is how much cash
you would need to hold alongside the
underlying equities in each case such
that the ending wealth for the covered
calls fund and the portfolio of the
underlying equities plus cash have the
same ending wealth. Again, holding
withdrawals constant. Remember that
covered calls reduce your exposure to
the underlying equities asymmetrically
by capping upside while leaving downside
mostly exposed. Another way to reduce
your exposure to an equity is to
explicitly reduce your exposure to it by
selling some of your position and then
holding the sale proceeds in a low-risk
investment like a high interest savings
account. I found that the cash
allocation, the high interest savings
account allocation that make the wealth
outcomes equal range from 19% to 36%.
This means that in the most extreme case
in my examples, you could hold a
portfolio of 36% cash and 64% stock and
holding monthly spending constant at the
yield of the covered call fund have an
outcome equal to writing covered calls
on the same underlying equities. Again,
I am not suggesting that you should be
holding high cash allocations if you're
living off your portfolio, but I think
this is another great way to illustrate
the effect that cover calls have on
expected returns, including in cases
where the portfolio is funding cash flow
needs. It's similar to holding a whole
bunch of cash, except in the case of
covered calls, you're fully exposed to
the downside risk of the stock. At least
holding cash reduces downside risk
exposure. Again, this should not be
surprising. If you want income, creating
it yourself through a combination of
dividends and sales produces a better
expected outcome than writing covered
calls. Their high distribution yields
create the illusion of income. But that
income comes with a liability. The
capped upside on returns in the event
that the option is exercised. That at
least in these examples far more than
offsets the income. The other big
trade-off for long-term investors is
that by capping upside returns, you are
removing the mean reversion that
historical stock returns have exhibited.
After bad returns, stock returns tends
to bounce back. Those bouncebacks are
important to long-term returns and make
stocks a bit less risky than they would
be if returns were completely random. To
broaden my sample, I collected data for
20 Canadian listed covered call ETFs
with closely or identically matched ETFs
of the underlying holdings and I
compared their performance. To be clear,
we are back to total return comparisons
now, not withdrawal analysis, just
because it's a short time series of
data. In cases where the covered call
fund is not an index fund, I found a
fund with a high holdings overlap and
high return correlation to compare it to
for the underlying. I excluded really
niche funds and those without any
obvious comparables for the underlying.
This speaks to another problem that I
see with a lot of these products.
They're often really, really niche
sector funds and they often hold
concentrated, actively managed
underlying portfolios. Those sector bets
and the individual stock risk and the
active management all add to the risk of
these products for long-term investors.
I limited my sample to funds with at
least one year of history. I know that's
still way too short to draw conclusions
from, but this is what I had to work
with. There's just not a lot of funds
with really long histories. And the
newer funds tell the exact same story as
the older ones. Out of the 20 funds,
only two have outperformed a comparable
underlying equity fund. Both of them
were technology covered call funds with
fairly short histories and imperfectly
matched underlying equity portfolios.
So, I wouldn't read too much into those
two that under outperformed. On average,
the covered call funds in this sample
underperform comparable underlying
equity funds by an annualized 3.25
percentage points and the median
underperformance is 2.96 percentage
points. As we saw earlier, this
underperformance matters for both
accumulators and people drawing from
their portfolios. The last point I'll
cover is what are generally called
enhanced covered call funds. These funds
not only employ a covered call strategy,
but also use leverage to increase their
yield and their expected returns. I'll
be honest, these things are fascinating
pieces of financial technology. The
problem though is that the history of
financial innovation has tended to
create profits for financial product
manufacturers at the expense of end
investors. That aside, I think you have
to appreciate how incredible it is that
a fairly complex portfolio like this is
available under a single ticker. For
better or for worse, let's look at some
enhanced covered call funds. To keep it
simple, I will look at the Global X
index series of funds. Since they have
ETFs for the underlying, the underlying
with covered calls and enhanced versions
for both, they are targeting a leverage
ratio of 125% in their enhanced funds.
Across five index funds, all over
periods where returns have been overall
positive for the underlying equities,
the performance of the enhanced covered
call fund is above the regular covered
call funds and below the returns of the
underlying equities. The leverage
covered call funds have also performed
worse than the others during periods of
negative returns. What we'll generally
see is that leverage boosts returns of
these portfolios when times are good and
makes their draw downs more severe when
times are bad. No surprises there.
Overall though, leverage has helped all
of these enhanced funds outperform their
notenhanced covered call counterparts
over this short period, which should be
expected again when returns are
positive. Leverage is not a bad thing,
but I find the case for applying
leverage to a covered call fund to be a
little bit odd. Remember, covered calls
are capping upside and not helping much
on the downside. Leverage is enhancing
both the upside and the downside. If
you're comfortable with higher
volatility and leverage, leveraging the
underlying equity without writing calls
likely makes more sense. The data
support this. In all five of my example
funds, the leveraged version of the
underlying has outperformed the
underlying, the covered call fund, and
the leveraged cover call fund. One last
thing I want to address is whether I, as
a financial professional, feel
threatened by covered call funds, which
is something that has come up a few
times since I made my last video. The
idea seems to be that these products are
so good that they will put wealth
management firms out of business
entirely. They won't. Wealth management
is about much more than creating an
income stream in retirement. Expert
financial advice can be categorized into
areas where knowledge of base rates,
technical competence in financial
planning, and an understanding of human
psychology can be applied to help people
arrive at highquality financial
decisions. Those areas are goal
formation and quantification, asset
allocation, cash flow planning,
insurance needs analysis, financial
product allocation, and tax awareness.
Covered calls may kind of sort of solve
cash flow planning, but that's about it.
I also have some comments on where the
information promoting covered calls is
coming from. It is a requirement in
Canada for content creators to disclose
when their content is sponsored. This is
intended to avoid hidden conflicts of
interest. A lot of the content out there
promoting covered calls as a strategy
is, drum roll, sponsored by companies
selling covered call ETFs. This is
obviously a conflict of interest. At
least it isn't hidden, but it still
warrants caution. I have my own
conflicts of interest to be clear. I
work for PWL Capital which is a wealth
management firm. It is good for us if
people decide to delegate their
portfolio management and the financial
planning that informs that portfolio
management to us. But we have nothing to
gain or lose based on whether you invest
in covered call funds. As discretionary
portfolio managers, we can and as
fiduciaries, we must use covered call
ETFs in our clients portfolios if we
believe that is what is in the client's
best interest. We do not use them
because we think they are detrimental to
investors at any stage in life for the
reasons I have shown in this video and
in my last video. Other than the
psychological pacification that may come
from income distributions, these funds,
in my opinion, do not have any redeeming
qualities. I urge any investors who've
been wooed by the promise of so-called
passive income to ensure that they
understand exactly what they're
investing in and why those specific
investment characteristics are worth the
high implied costs I have detailed in
this video. I also implore you to
understand where you are getting your
information and what the information
sources incentives are. Thanks for
watching. I'm Ben Felix, chief
investment officer at PWL Capital. If
you enjoyed this video, please share
with someone who is not yet aware of the
high implied costs of covered calls.